<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Iacobs vovv A sermon preached before his Maiestie, and the Prince his Highnesse, at Hampton Court, September. 23. 1621. By Christopher Swale, Doctor of Diuinitie, and one of his Maiesties chaplaines in ordinarie.</title>
            <title>Jacobs vow.</title>
            <author>Swale, Christopher, d. 1645.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13214</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23512</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106180</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841903</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841903</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6518</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13214)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6518)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 582:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Iacobs vovv A sermon preached before his Maiestie, and the Prince his Highnesse, at Hampton Court, September. 23. 1621. By Christopher Swale, Doctor of Diuinitie, and one of his Maiesties chaplaines in ordinarie.</title>
                  <title>Jacobs vow.</title>
                  <author>Swale, Christopher, d. 1645.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6518:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6518:1"/>
            <p>IACOBS VOVV.</p>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before his MAIESTIE, and the PRINCE his Highneſſe, <hi>At</hi> HAMPTON COVRT, <hi>September.</hi> 23. 1621.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Christopher Swale,</hi> Doctor of Diuinitie, and one of his MAIESTIES Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines in Ordinarie.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>John Bill.</hi> 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:6518:2"/>
            <head>The Text.</head>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gen. chap. 28. verſ. 20. 21. 22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>20. Then <hi>Iacob</hi> vowed a Vow, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, If God will be with me, and will keepe mee in this way that I goe, and will giue me bread to eat, and raiment to put on.</p>
               <p>21. So that I come againe to my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe in peace, then ſhall the Lord be my God.</p>
               <p>22. And this Stone, which I haue ſet vp as a Pillar, ſhalbe Gods houſe: and of all that thou ſhalt giue mee, I will ſurely giue the Tenth vnto thee.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6518:2"/>
            <head>IACOBS Vovv.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HICH words are the Vowe of that holy Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arke <hi>Iacob,</hi> who being mortally hated of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Eſau,</hi> for deceiuing him (as he tearmed it) both of his Birth-right, and of his Bleſſing, was forced to flie for his life: And by the aduiſe of his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with the expreſſe conſent, and commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Father in the firſt verſe of this chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, hee trauailed towards <hi>Padan-Aran</hi> vnto his vnckle <hi>Laban</hi> for ſuccour; in hope there not onely to haue his life ſecured fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his brothers rage; but alſo to be prouided of a Wife, amongſt his owne kindred, which might be a helper, and comforter vnto him: yet he went not forth like a Woer, nor like either his father <hi>Iſaacs</hi> ſonne, or his grandfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:<note place="margin">Gen. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeruant, with Gamels, and Men,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6518:3"/>and Iewels, and other prouiſion for ſuch a iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, (for then perhappes hee had neuer made this Vowe,) but hee went all alone like a poore Pilgrime, with his ſtaffe in his hand, and ſo came wearie, and late (the Sunne being downe) vnto a certaine place, neere vnto <hi>Haran,</hi> where he tooke vp his lodging for that night:<note place="margin">Homil. 54. in Gen.</note> and as Saint <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſostome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ibi dormiuit, vbi nox eum comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit,</hi> He ſlept there where he was benighted, not in any towne or houſe; or tent, but <hi>Sub dio,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the earth his bed, heauen his canopie, and a ſtone (which hee found in that place) the pillow whereupon he repoſed his head: and yet hauing a wearied bodie, and a quiet conſcience (which are two good Engines, to draw on ſleepe) he ſlept as ſoundly vpon that hard pillow, as if hee had lien vpon a bed of Downe: And in his ſleepe he drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of a certaine Ladder reaching vp from earth to heauen, vpon which the Angels of God aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and deſcended, and the Lord himſelfe ſtood at the toppe of the Ladder; who made vnto him a large, and a moſt gracious foure-fold promiſe, in the 13.14. and 15. verſes. 1. That he would giue vnto him and his ſeed, that land vpon which he then ſlept. 2. That hee would multiply his ſeede as the duſt of the earth. 3. That in his ſeed, all the Nations of the earth ſhould be Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; And laſtly, that he would be with him, and keepe him whitherſoeuer hee went, and bring him againe vnto that land, and not to forſake him vntill he had performed all, that he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed vnto him.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:6518:3"/>
            <p>When <hi>Iacob</hi> awoke out of his ſleepe, and perceiued that the Lord was in that place, and he not aware of it, and that that place was no other, but the <hi>houſe of God, and gate of heauen,</hi> verſe 17. he was ſtricken with feare and reuerence, as euery one ought to bee, that commeth within the gate of Gods houſe, and tooke the ſtone that lay vnder his head, and ſet it vp for a pillar, and powred oyle vpon the top of it, and called the name of that place <hi>Bethel,</hi> that is, <hi>the houſe of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And entring into a ſerious conſideration of this gracious Promiſe, which farre exceeded all that hee could either aske, or thinke, hee did not through vnbeliefe make any doubt of the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance thereof; but certainely belieuing that it ſhould be accompliſhed in due time, like a thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Pilgrime, or a man euen ouer-ioyed with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected, but yet aſſured hopes; he began to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die with himſelfe, what hee ſhould render vnto the Lord, for all theſe benefits promiſed vnto him; and not finding any better meanes to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe his thankefulneſſe, he vowed a Vow in my Text, ſaying, <hi>If God will be with me, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of which Vow there be two parts. The firſt is, <hi>Petitio,</hi> a Requeſt, which he deſired of God; The ſecond is, <hi>Promiſsio,</hi> a dutie, which he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to performe to God.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Petition</hi> in theſe words, <hi>If God will be with me, and will keepe me in this way that I goe, and will giue me bread to eat, and raiment to put on, ſo that I come againe to my fathers houſe in peace;</hi> The dutie
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6518:4"/>which hee promiſeth to performe in liew of this benefit is three-fold. 1. <hi>That the Lord ſhall be his God.</hi> 2. <hi>That the ſtone which he had ſet vp for a pillar, ſhould be Gods houſe.</hi> 3. <hi>That of all that God ſhould giue him, he would giue vnto God the Tenth.</hi> Of which points in order as they lie in the Text.</p>
            <p>And firſt of the Petition, or requeſt, which (as you ſee) is very moderate, and reaſonable: for whereas God had promiſed vnto <hi>Iacob</hi> foure things; <hi>Iacob</hi> doth not deſire all, nor halfe, nor the thirde part of that which was promiſed, but contenteth himſelfe with the laſt, and leaſt of all thoſe foure things, and deſireth nothing, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſaries for the preſent; not <hi>Quailes,</hi> or <hi>Manna</hi> for delight; but onely bread for neceſſitie, that is neceſſarie food: not purple and fine linnen for pompe; but onely raiment to put on, that is, neceſſarie cloathes: not the attendance of many feruants; but onely the protection, and bleſſing of God, without which, neither his food, nor rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor any thing els could doe him good, nor himſelfe, either be well, or be.</p>
            <p>But what is the reaſon why <hi>Iſaac,</hi> who was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding rich, ſent foorth his ſonne <hi>Iacob</hi> (who by Gods prouidence was now lately made his Heire) ſo exceeding poore, that he is faine to petition for foode and raiment, whereas <hi>Abraham</hi> his father, ſent foorth his very ſeruant vpon the like iourney richly furniſhed, and ſumptuouſly attended? Was <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeruant better then <hi>Iſaacs</hi> ſonne?</p>
            <p>To omit the diuers Allegories which Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Ser, de te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por. <hi>79.</hi> Gre. mor. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Gregorie</hi> haue obſerued vpon this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6518:4"/>the reaſons, as <hi>Theodoret</hi> and others haue well ſummed them vp, might be theſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>Vt fratr is conatus melius declinaret,</hi> that going poorely, and priuately, his brother <hi>Eſau</hi> might not ſo eaſily miſſe him, nor know which way to purſue after him.</item>
               <item>2. That this miſerie might mooue his brother to compaſſion, and reconciliation.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Vt animus eſſet reuertendi,</hi> that carrying no wealth with him to maintaine, or detaine him abroad, he might haue the more mind to returne vnto his father home againe.</item>
               <item>4. And laſtly, that hee might haue the better experience of Gods mercie, as indeede he had, for which hee returned thankes vnto God at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne in the 32. chap.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Iacobs</hi> pouertie may teach vs, that although worldly proſperitie be the good bleſſing of God, wherewith he often enricheth his owne children: yet hee euer, at one time or other, chaſteneth thoſe, whom he loueth, and traineth them vp in his ſchoole of affliction, and nurtureth them with his <hi>Ferula</hi> of wants and croſſes. <hi>Virgatua &amp; bacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus tuus,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt &amp;c.<note place="margin">Pſal. 23.4.</note> they muſt as well be humbled, and inſtructed with his rod of correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as ſupported with his ſtaffe of comfort. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and <hi>Iſaac, Iob,</hi> and <hi>Dauid,</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> alſo in my Text, after his returne from <hi>Padan-Aran,</hi> were all rich, and our Lord himſelfe was Lord of all, and yet none of them wanted either their wants or croſſes. And the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Gods owne people were not onely pinched with wants
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6518:5"/>in the wilderneſſe;<note place="margin">Ioſ. 23.13.</note> but were pricked with thornes in their eyes, and goades in their ſides, euen in the land of Promiſe.</p>
            <p>Whence wee may learne, that <hi>Aduerſitie</hi> is the bleſſing of God vpon his Children, aſwell as <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie. Res proſpera donum eſt conſolantis, res aduerſa donu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt admonent is Dei,</hi> ſaith S. Auguſtine, <hi>Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is the gift of God comforting, Aduerſitie the gift of God admoniſhing: Proſperity</hi> may bee the more pleaſant, but <hi>Aduerſitie</hi> many times is the more profitable: which made <hi>Dauid</hi> out of his own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience ingeniouſly confeſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.71.</note> that it was good for him, that hee had beene afflicted. And ſo it is good for vs all to be afflicted ſometimes, els we ſhould forget both God, and our ſelues, and bee too much wedded to this world, and ſay with Saint <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 17.4.</note> 
               <hi>Bonum eſt eſſe hic,</hi> and begin to build ſuch Tabernacles here vpon earth, as would hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vs from our euerlaſting Tabernacles of bliſſe in heauen. And thus much of <hi>Iacobs</hi> pouertie and want.</p>
            <p>But now being in ſo great want as hee was at this time, why doth he preferre ſo poore a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto God, who is ſo rich in mercie? And whereas God had now lately appeared vnto him here in <hi>Bethel,</hi> and promiſed the whole land of <hi>Canaan</hi> to him, and his, why doth hee deſire ſo poore a pittance, as food and raiment, which would onely keepe life and ſoule together? the very foules of the aire are furniſhed with theſe.</p>
            <p>And yet <hi>Iacob</hi> deſires no more, to teach vs, how moderate wee ſhould be in the deſire of earthly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6518:5"/>things. We may and ought to be euen couetous of things ſpirituall, and heauenly; ſo ſaith the Apoſtle: <hi>Couet after the beſt gifts:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.31.</note> but of tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and earthly things we may not be couetous, more then is neceſſary for our callings &amp; eſtates: becauſe as our Sauiour teacheth,<note place="margin">Luke 12.15.</note> 
               <hi>Amans life doth not conſiſt in the abundance of the things which hee poſſeſſeth.</hi> Therefore the Apoſtles rule is, that hauing but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> onely <hi>food</hi> and <hi>rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.8.</note> wee muſt be content therewith: for <hi>Victus, &amp; vestitus ſunt diuitiae Christianorum,</hi> ſaith Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome: <hi>food and raiment are the riches of Christians:</hi> and our patterne of Prayer doth warrant vs, to petition onely for our daily bread, that is, as it is excellently expounded in that <hi>Royall Meditation vpon the Lords Prayer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Written by the kings Maieſtie.</note> onely for ſuch temporall things, as are neceſſary for our <hi>Eſſe,</hi> or at fartheſt, for our <hi>Bene eſse.</hi> And they that cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with theſe, but with the Horſe-leaches daughters, ſtill cry, <hi>Giue, Giue;</hi> and will needes be rich, fall into temptation, and a ſnare, and into ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fooliſh, and hurtfull luſts, which drowne the ſoule in perdition, and deſtruction, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. <hi>Iacob</hi> hauing once ſeene God in <hi>Bethel,</hi> and ſet his heart vpon him, who is the true treaſure, neither admired, nor much deſired (more then was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary) this worldly traſh.</p>
            <p>Where wee may ſee, that howſoeuer world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings doe not onely admire, but euen adore riches, and honours, and earthly pleaſures, as their ſole trinitie, yet the Children of God, knowing that earthly honors, and riches are but ſhadowes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6518:6"/>of heauenly, and the pleaſures of ſinne, not ſo much as ſhadowes of heauenly pleaſures: vſe theſe things, when God giueth them; but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abuſe nor admire the ſame And why ſhould men admire ſhadowes, painted fires, which flame, but warme not? and may fitly be compared vnto Glo-wormes, or peices of rotten-wood, which in a darke night ſhine like ſtars, but when the Sunne ariſeth, and ſheweth what they are, the one ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth to be a poore worme, the other nothing but a rotten ſticke: So theſe glorious outward things, ſhine like Starres in the eyes of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of darkeneſſe: but the Children of light, whoſe eyes are purged from thoſe skales of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, doe plainely ſee, that in regard of true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, they be <hi>Vanit as vaniſsima,</hi> wormes, &amp; ſtickes, before which <hi>Solomon</hi> incomparably preferred wiſedome;<note place="margin">1. Kings 3.9.</note> and <hi>Agur</hi> in the <hi>Prouerbs</hi> of <hi>Solomon,</hi> prayed expreſſely againſt riches in the thirtieth Chapter, aſwell as pouertie. <hi>Mendicitatem, &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitias ne dederis mihi: Giue me neither pouertie, nor riches, but feed me with food conuenient for me.</hi> And this is the reaſon, why <hi>Iacob</hi> in my Text, petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons neither for riches, nor honour, nor any other outward thing, but onely for bread to eat, and cloathes to put on.</p>
            <p>And yet one thing more is to be obſerued in <hi>Iacobs</hi> Petition, out of theſe words of my Text, where he ſaith, <hi>If God will be with me, and keepe me in this way, that I goe, and bring me againe to my fathers houſe in peace;</hi> wherein beſides foode, and raiment, you ſee hee deſireth the protection, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6518:6"/>bleſſing of God in his whole iourney going out, and comming in: without which, neither his bread could nouriſh, nor his cloathes keepe him warme, nor any thing elſe doe him good. For <hi>Man doth not liue by bread onely,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>but by euery word which proceedeth out of the mouth of God,</hi> that is, the bleſſing of God vpon bread: For as in Phiſicke, a diſeaſed man is preſcribed to boile certaine medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinable hearbes in running water, and then to drinke a quantity of that water, and ſo is cured of his diſeaſe: and yet wee know, that it is not the water, but the decoction, or infuſion which cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Patient: ſo it is not the bread that nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth, nor the abundance of outward things, which enricheth, or contenteth, but the infuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gods bleſſing, which is the ſtaffe of bread; without which a man may ſtarue for hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,<note place="margin">Leuit. 26.26. Ezek. 4.16.</note> with bread in his mouth, and die like the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> with the fleſh of Quailes in their teeth.<note place="margin">Pſal. 78.31.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas on the contrary, <hi>Daniel</hi> feeding vpon bare pulſe, ſtrengthened by the bleſſing of God, which is the ſtaffe of bread, and of all other nouriſhment, was fatter, and fairer,<note place="margin">Dan. 1.15.</note> then they that were fed with the Kings diet: For it is the bleſsing of God, that maketh rich: and a little,<note place="margin">Pro 10.22.</note> that the righteous hath,<note place="margin">Pro. 16.8.</note> is better then the great reuenewes of the vngodly. And wee may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue in our owne experience, many a man, who with a dinner of greene hearbes,<note place="margin">Pro. 15.87.</note> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, that is ſhort diet, courſe clothes, hard lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and a poore eſtate, looketh fatter, liueth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6518:7"/>merrier, ſleepeth ſweetlier, enioyeth more hearts eaſe, and true content, and in trueth liueth better then others that weare a chaine of golde. And therfore wiſely did <hi>Iacob</hi> deſire nothing but food, and raiment, and Gods bleſſing vpon them, which hee knew would ſerue his turne. And thus much of the Petition, or Requeſt which <hi>Iacob</hi> deſired of God.</p>
            <p>Now I come to the duties, which he promiſeth to performe to God, in the next words, <hi>Then ſhall the Lord be my God, &amp;c.</hi> herein <hi>Iacob,</hi> who was afterward ſurnamed <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 32.</note> hauing receiued but euen the promiſe of a benefit, preſently voweth the performance of a duetie, to teach all true <hi>Iſrae</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, that <hi>Beneficium poſtulat of ficium:</hi> and that the thankefulneſſe of the receiuer, ought to anſwere vnto the benefit of the beſtower, as the Eccho an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth to the voice: wee doe no ſooner receiue the one, but we are immediatly bound to returne the other.<note place="margin">Pſal. 116.</note> So doth <hi>Dauid, Thou haſt deliuered my ſoule from death, mine eyes from teares, and my feet from falling,</hi> There is the benefite receiued; and then it followeth in the very next words, <hi>I will walke before the Lord in the land of the liuing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe. 9.</note> there is the duetie returned: So likewiſe in my Text, <hi>If God will be with me, and giue me bread to eate, and cloathes to put on,</hi> there is the benefit petitioned for, and promiſe, <hi>Then ſhall the Lord be my God, &amp;c.</hi> there is the returne of a duetie vowed.</p>
            <p>Now wee all haue receiued the ſame or the like benefits, both ſpirituall and temporall, whereby we are all bound vnto the like thankefulneſſe; but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6518:7"/>where is the performance of the ſame, or the like duties? We owe as much, or more vnto God for his benefits, then <hi>Iacob</hi> did, but who voweth, or paieth vnto him the like duties, that <hi>Iacob</hi> did? What heart can thinke, or what tongue can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe our infinite obligations? Firſt for ſpirituall fauours: Infinitely are we bound vnto God for our Creation: more then infinitely (if more might be) for our Redemption, and our effectuall Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vnto the participation thereof. What ſhall we then render vnto the Lord, for all theſe bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits done vnto vs? <hi>Totum me debeo,</hi> ſaith S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, <hi>pro me facto: quid igitur rependam pro me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempto? Iowe euery whit of my ſelfe</hi> (vnto God) <hi>for my Creation, what ſhall I then render vnto him for my Redemption?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Ambr. ſuper lue. ſer. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nihileſt quod dignum referre poſſumus pro ſuſcepta carne Maria, quid pro cruce obita, quid pro verberibus, &amp; ſepultura redde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus? We are not able to be ſufficiently thankefull for taking our fleſh of the</hi> (Virgin) <hi>Marie, what ſhall wee then returne vnto him for his ſuffering vpon the Croſſe, for his ſtripes, for his buriall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for temporall benefits, we are farre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Iacob;</hi> he wandred vp and downe the world like a poore Pilgrime, with his ſtaffe in his hand: he kept ſheepe, and was parched with the heat of the day, and frozen with the cold of the night; and in my Text, the bare earth was his bedde, a hard ſtone his pillow; he had nothing, he deſired nothing, but onely bread to eate, and cloathes to put on, and the protection and bleſſing of God
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6518:8"/>vpon him in his iourney, and yet hee, euen for theſe vowed a Vow vnto God. Wee ſit vnder our owne Vines, and our owne Fig-trees in peace and reſt,<note place="margin">Amos 6.4, 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>We lie vpon beds of Iuorie, and ſtretch our ſelues vpon our couches; we are clad in purple and fine linnen, and fare delicately euery day; we eat calues out of the ſtalles, and lambes out of the flockes; wee drinke wine in boules, and annoint our ſelues with coſtly oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and inuent instruments of Muſicke</hi> (like Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid.) <hi>But who is either ſorrie for the affliction of</hi> Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph, the extreame miſeries of our Brethren in neighbour-Countries, or who is ſenſible of our owne great proſperitie, and our incomparable happineſſe, or who for all this voweth one Vow to God?</p>
            <p>When our Sauiour CHRIST had cleanſed ten Leapers,<note place="margin">Luke 17.17.</note> there was but one found amongſt all thoſe ten, &amp; he a ſtranger too, that returned to giue God thanks. I feare there is ſcarſely one of an hundred amongſt vs, that is but euen ſo thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto God for all his benefits, as that ſtranger was onely for his cleanſing.</p>
            <p>When this good Patriarke <hi>Iacob</hi> returned rich from <hi>Padan-Aran</hi> in the 32. chapter of this booke, he neither forgate what he was then, nor what he had beene before: and therefore in a thankefull remembrance of Gods great mercies towards him, he payed one part of this Vow in that place, and worſhipped God,<note place="margin">Gen. 32.10.</note> ſaying, <hi>O Lord, I am not worthy of the leaſt of all thy mercies. for with my ſtaſſe I paſſed ouer this Iordan, and now I am become two bands.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:6518:8"/>
            <p>Many a one there be in this honourable Court, who haue paſſed ouer, not the riuer of <hi>Iordan,</hi> but the riuer of <hi>Trent,</hi> or <hi>Thames,</hi> or <hi>Seuerne</hi> with their ſtaues in their hands, that is, poore eſtates in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, and haue beene deliuered from many dangers, and are now euen laden with riches and honours; And yet I doubt there bee not manie, that for all this, haue vowed with <hi>Iacob,</hi> to haue the Lord for their God, or to build him an Houſe, or to pay him the Tenth of all that he hath giuen them.</p>
            <p>One Religious Vow, you ſee weekely payed in this place by our royall <hi>Iacob,</hi> I meane our Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes Exerciſe; which was deuoutly vowed, vpon as iuſt an occaſion, as euer Vow was made. And hitherto (God be thanked) it hath beene religiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed. God grant that this our <hi>Iacob</hi> may long, and long liue a happie King of this happie Iſland, euen as long (if it bee his will) as the olde Patriarke <hi>Iacob</hi> did, to pay this tribute, and the reſt of his Vowes vnto the King of Kings. And can wee that are his ſeruants, haue a better pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne to imitate, then the Religious example of ſo Royall a Maſter? therefore I will conclude this point, with that zealous exhortation of another King, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.11. <hi>Vouete &amp; reddite Domino Deo vestro. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ow vnto the Lord your God, and keepe it, all yee that are round about him: bring preſents vnto him that ought to be feared.</hi> And thus much of the generall of <hi>Iacobs</hi> Vow.</p>
            <p>Now I come to the particular duties vowed; and they are three. Firſt, that the Lord ſhould
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6518:9"/>be his God, that is, that hee would worſhip the true God, and no other. Secondly, that the ſtone which hee had ſet vp for a pillar, ſhould be Gods houſe: that is, he would dedicate that place vnto the publique worſhip of God. Thirdly, for the maintenance of both theſe, he would giue the Tenth of all that hee had. All which were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary duties, and euery one of them hath a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary relation, and dependance vpon other; For if God muſt be worſhipped, then muſt hee haue a place to be worſhipped in, which is here called an Houſe, and our SAVIOVR ſaith,<note place="margin">Mar. 11.17.</note> ſhall of all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions bee called the Houſe of Prayer; And if a Houſe of Prayer, then a maintenance for that Houſe, and them that ſhall ſay Prayers in it. Of theſe in order, and firſt of the firſt.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Then ſhall the Lord be my God.</head>
               <p>To haue the LORD for our GOD, is the very ſumme of the firſt Commandement, the meaning whereof, as all Interpreters expound it, is to loue God aboue all, to make him our treaſure, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely to preferre him, and his Seruice before our ſelues, and all other things in the world. A duetie whereunto euery man is bound, as well as <hi>Iacob,</hi> and euery man that is not an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> will confeſſe, and profeſſe as much: But how they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme this dutie, or either loue, or preferre God aboue all, who ſo farre preferre themſelues, their honours, pleaſures and profits vnto Gods Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, that they ſpend more houres of time, and pounds of money vpon the one, then minutes, or pence vpon the other; and beſtow more coſt euen
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6518:9"/>vpon points and ſhooe-ſtrings in one day, then vpon the worſhipping of God in a whole yeere, iudge ye. <hi>Aures omnium pulſo, conſcientias ſingulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum conuenio,</hi> as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh. If the Lord be their God, where is his feare? where is his loue? where is his honour? there goeth more to this, then the hearing of a Sermon once, or twiſe a weeke; eſpecially as it is vſually heard, which is ſcarce worth the name of a hearing: and <hi>Iacob</hi> meant more then ſo in my Text. For to haue the Lord for our God, is to loue him aboue all, as I ſaid before, and to ſerue him <hi>Semper, &amp; ad ſemper,</hi> with an vniuerſall obedience, both in regard of time and place, and with <hi>Dauid</hi> to haue reſpect, not vnto ſome one, or two;<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.6.</note> but vnto all his Commandements. They which ſerue God on the Sundaies, but not on the weeke-dayes; in the Church, not in their Chambers, Cloſets, Callings, and whole courſe of life; and that, not for praiſe, profit, pleaſing of men, or cuſtome; but out of a good and honeſt heart, and a conſcience of their duties, doe not performe this part of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> Vow, to haue the Lord for their God. And thus much of the firſt dutie.</p>
               <p>The ſecond followeth in the next words, <hi>And this ſtone, which I haue ſet vp for a pillar, ſhalbe Gods Houſe.</hi> A dutie neceſſarily depending vpon the former; for if God muſt be worſhipped, then muſt he haue a place to be worſhipped in, here called an Houſe.</p>
               <p>Now ſome thinke, that this place where <hi>Iacob</hi> ſlept, and ſet vp this Pillar, was <hi>Mount Moria,</hi> and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6518:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>that he called it <hi>Bethel,</hi> or the Houſe of God, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetically by a <hi>Prolepſis,</hi> becauſe the Temple ſhould afterwards bee built there: yet there may be two other reaſons, why <hi>Iacob</hi> calleth this pillar Gods Houſe, as before he called the very place <hi>Bethel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe God had manifeſted his preſence here, in an extraordinary manner, as he did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards both in the wandring tabernacle, and in the fixed Temple, where he was, therefore ſaid to dwell,<note place="margin">1. King. 8.13.</note> as in an Houſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe <hi>Iacob</hi> conſecrated this place vnto the Seruice of God, and <hi>chap.</hi> 35. <hi>and</hi> 14. <hi>verſe,</hi> ſet vp an Altar for his worſhip in ſtead of this Pillar, and (as may probably be thought) would haue built a Houſe for Prayer, and ſacrificed in this place, if him ſelfe, and the Church had beene then ſetled here, and had opportunitie, and meanes to haue done it. But being a Pilgrime, and in his iourney, he did what he could for the preſent, he anointed a Pillar, erected an Altar for Sacrifice, and dedicated a place for an Houſe of Prayer; whereby we may ſee what great care this holy Patriarke had of the place of Gods worſhip: his firſt care was for the worſhip it ſelfe, which hee vowed in the former words: his next care is of the place of his worſhip, in theſe words.</p>
               <p>To teach vs, that as our firſt care ſhould be of the worſhip of God: ſo our ſecond care ſhould be of the place of his worſhip. The obiect of our firſt loue, muſt be God him ſelfe: the obiect of our ſecond loue, muſt be the Houſe of God. <hi>O Lord, I
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6518:10"/>haue loued the habitation of thy houſe, and the place where thine honour dwelleth,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.8. <hi>Thy ſeruants take pleaſure in her ſtones, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour the very duſt thereof.</hi> Pſal. 102.14. And Pſal. 84.10. <hi>One day in thy Courts, is better then a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand. I had rather be a doore-keeper in the houſe of my God, then to dwell in the tents of wickedneſſe:</hi> And he rendreth the reaſon, why he ſo exceedingly lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Houſe of God, in the very next verſe: for there <hi>the Lord is the ſunne and ſhield,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>11</label> 
                  <hi>there hee will giue grace and glorie: and no good thing will he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold from them that liue a godly life.</hi> God is in all places by a generall prouidence, but hee dwelleth in his houſe by a ſpeciall preſence. Hee diſtilleth the droppes of his mercie vpon euery part of the earth, but hee powreth it downe vpon that holy ground which is dedicate to his Seruice. There, be ſhineth like the Sunne: there, hee defendeth like a ſhield hee filled the Temple at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> with his glorie: hee made many gracious promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to them that praied therein, or towards it and ſtill <hi>where two or three are gathered together in his Name, hee will be in the middeſt amongst them:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 18.20.</note> and no good thing will he with-hold from them, that worſhip him in the beautie of holineſſe, and wait for his <hi>louing kindneſſe in the middeſt of his Temple.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 48.9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Priuate Conuenticles are not to be compared with the publique Aſſemblies of the Church that is both the throne of Gods glorie, and his Mercie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeat.</p>
               <p>Which euer ſo inflamed the holy men of God
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6518:11"/>in former ages with the zeale of his Houſe, that they ſpared neither coſt, nor paines, nor euer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected any thing ſo much, as the building and beautifying thereof. <hi>I will not ſuffer mine eyes to ſleepe, nor my eye-lids to ſlumber</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi>) <hi>vntill I find out a place for the Lord, an habitation for the mightie God of Iacob.</hi> Pſal. 132.<note place="margin">Luke 7.5.</note> The good Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion in the Goſpel builded a Synagogue at his owne charges. Great <hi>Constantine,</hi> that mirrour of deuotion, bare twelue baskets of earth vpon his owne ſhoulders towards the founding of a Church. And when that noble Captaine <hi>Teren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> had done ſuch ſeruice in <hi>Armenia,</hi> that the Emperour <hi>Valens</hi> bade him aske whatſoeuer hee would, for a reward of his ſeruice, his onely ſuite (as <hi>Theodoret</hi> reporteth) was <hi>vt Orthodoxis vna praeberetur Eccleſia:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hiſt. tripart. lib. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> And when the Emperour tare his petition, and bade him aske ſomewhat els, hee ſtill perſiſted in his ſuite, and called God to record, that hee would make no other ſuit but that. And how zealous our owne forefathers haue beene in this kinde of deuotion, I need not ſpeake, the zeale of Gods Houſe did euen eate them vp: the goodly Monuments whereof, yet extant in all our Cities, and many Countey-Pariſhes (which haue ſpared vs both the labour, and charge of building Houſes vnto God) ſpeake for them. But ſome of thoſe Houſes which they haue built, and euen the faireſt of them, ſince their Buttereſſes, and Pillars (I meane their maintenance) hath beene pluckt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, begin to droope alreadie, and in time, (if it be not preuented) will moulder away, and drop
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6518:11"/>downe: And yet who pittieth the ruines of Sion, on repaireth any one wall, or window thereof? <hi>Will your ſelues dwell in ſieled houſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hag. 1.4.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſuffer the Houſes of God to lie waſte?</hi> Shall <hi>Pater noster</hi> build Churches, and <hi>Our father</hi> pull them downe? (as the prouerbe is) or ſuffer them to fall?<note place="margin">2. Sam. 1.20</note> 
                  <hi>O let not that be told in</hi> Gath, <hi>nor publiſhed in the ſtreetes of</hi> Askalon, <hi>leſt the Philiſtines reioyce, leſt the vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed triumph.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore to conclude this point, Seeing wee need not with <hi>Iacob</hi> in my Text, vow to build: let vs all out of our zeale vnto Gods Houſe, vow to beautifie, or at leaſt to keepe vp thoſe Houſes, which are built to our hands. And thus much of the ſecond duetie, which <hi>Iacob</hi> vowed in theſe words, <hi>This ſtone which I haue ſet vp, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third followeth in the laſt words, <hi>And of all that thou ſhalt giue me, I will giue the Tenth vnto thee.</hi> A duetie neceſſarily depending vpon the two former, as I ſaid before: For if God muſt be worſhipped, and haue an Houſe, then muſt there of neceſſitie be a maintenance: therefore <hi>Iacob</hi> in the third place, for a perpetuall maintenance of the worſhip, and houſe of God, and them that ſhall attend therein, voweth for himſelfe, and all the poſteritie, as well of his Faith, as Fleſh, vnto the end of the world, the paiment of Tithes; <hi>Of all that thou ſhalt giue mee, I will ſurely giue the Tenth vnto thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what is the reaſon why <hi>Iacob</hi> here voweth to giue vnto God rather the Tenth then any other part of his goods? Surely howſoeuer ſome other
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6518:12"/>cauſes may bee alleadged, yet the true reaſon is, becauſe <hi>Iacob</hi> knew, either by the light of Nature, or by the tradition and practiſe of his Anceſtors, that this <hi>quota,</hi> the very tenth, and no other part, was, is, and for euer muſt be as due vnto God, as either his Houſe, or his worſhip: therefore he ioyneth theſe three together, being all relatiues which depend one vpon another; <hi>Se mutuo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunt, &amp; auferunt,</hi> and they are all equally due vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God: And due vnto him, not by any common right, as other things, but by a ſpeciall proprietie, and right of reſeruation: whereby Almighty God from the very Creation of the world, and dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof vnto the vſe of men, reſerued vnto himſelfe, and ſeparated from common vſe, vnto his owne Seruice, ſome out of euery one of theſe fiue things, which ſhould neuer after be alienated, or taken away without Sacriledge.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. A forme of Diuine worſhip, which may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be giuen to any other.</item>
                  <item>2. A time for this worſhip, which is the Saboth day, neuer to be abrogated.</item>
                  <item>3. A place of worſhip, which is his Houſe, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to be prophaned.</item>
                  <item>4. A Prieſt-hood, which may neuer bow knee vnto Baal.</item>
                  <item>5. And laſtly, for the maintenance of all theſe, Tithes, which hee therefore calleth his owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, neuer without Sacriledge to be impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated.<note place="margin">Ambr. Ser. <hi>34.</hi> in feria tertia poſt <hi>1.</hi> Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam, quadrageſ. in vlt. edit. col.</note> 
                     <hi>De omni ſubſtantia quam Deus homini donat, decimam partem ſibi reſeruauit. Of all the ſubſtance which God hath giuen vnto man, he hath reſerued the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6518:12"/>Tenth part vnto himſelfe.</hi> They be the very words of Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> And S. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Aug. de temp. Ser. <hi>219.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Deus ſibi tantum decimam vendicans, nobis omnia condona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. God challenging only to himſelfe the Tenth, hath giuen all things vnto vs.</hi> And that hee reſerued to himſelfe the tithes for this purpoſe, euen from the beginning, as well as any of the other foure things may appeare by this; That for any thing we know to the contrary, tithes were payed euen from the beginning of the world: for ſome thinke, that <hi>Caine,</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> offered the very tithe as they were inſtructed of their father <hi>Adam:</hi> But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer that be, certaine it is, that there is no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner mention made of any Prieſt <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> of an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der fit to receiue them, then there is mention of paying of tithes vnto him. For <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of the Faithfull, no ſooner met with <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe dec</hi> a Prieſt of an Order, but for an example vnto all his poſteritie, euen all the Faithfull, vnto the end of the world, hee gaue him tithes of all the ſpoiles. <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. And gaue it him, not as an arbitrarie gift; but as a neceſſarie due vnto God: for hee ſware not to take ſo much as a Shooe-lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chet of the King of <hi>Sodoms,</hi> And yet hee tooke the tithe, to offer, not as his, but as Gods due. And <hi>Iacob</hi> in my Text, amongſt other Morrall dueties (for here is nothing Ceremoniall) voweth the paying of tithes: and in the 27. of <hi>Leuiticus,</hi> which is the firſt place where tithes are mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnder the Law, God doth not then begin to reſerue them, and to ſay, <hi>All the tithes of the land
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6518:13"/>ſhalbe the Lords;</hi> but claimeth them as his due of old by ancient inheritance, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>30</label> ſaying, <hi>All the tithe is the Lords, it is holy vnto the Lord;</hi> not it ſhall be. And ſo being his owne of old, he onely aſſigneth them vnto the Leuiticall Prieſt-hood for that time. And thus you ſee them due, both before, and vnder the Law.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Now let any man ſhew, when, and where they were abrogated by the Goſpell? Not by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour CHRIST, who ſpeaketh of them twiſe, or thriſe, and ſo had iuſt occaſion to haue abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated them, if he had had any ſuch intent; yet hee abrogateth not, but rather confirmeth them. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. <hi>Haec oportuit facere;</hi> Theſe things ought you to haue done. Nor by the Apoſtle, for S. <hi>Paul</hi> is ſo farre from abrogating, that on the contrary he both commandeth, and eſtabliſheth them, and prooueth them due. He commandeth them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Let him that is taught in the word communicate with him that teacheth,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in all good things. Indeed he nameth not the very <hi>Quotum,</hi> how much they were to communicate, as taking it for graunted, that the <hi>Galathians</hi> themſelues knew that to be the trueth, both by the light of Nature, and by the Scriptures, and by the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall practiſe of the Church, and by the practiſe of the Heathen themſelues, who vſed to offer their Tithes to their Idoles.</p>
               <p>And 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. hee plainely eſtabliſheth for a perpetuall ordinance the paying of Tithes: for ſaith he, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>14</label> 
                  <hi>Euen ſo hath the Lord or dained, that they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6518:13"/>which preach the Goſpel, ſhould liue of the Goſpel.</hi> Euen ſo, (that is as appeareth) out of the former verſe, <hi>As they that miniſtred about holy things in the Temple,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>13</label> 
                  <hi>liued vpon thoſe holy things, and they that waited vpon the Altar, liued of the Altar:</hi> Euen ſo muſt the Miniſters of the Goſpel liue, vpon the ſelfe ſame maintenance. Now how liued they? Indeed the Prieſts of the Law had other emoluments, which were Ceremoniall, and temporarie: but their principall, morall, certaine, and perpetuall main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance was out of thoſe ordinarie, and annuall Tithes, which are Gods ſtanding Inheritance; therefore of them muſt the Prieſts of the Goſpell liue; Euen ſo (ſaith the Apoſtle) hath the Lord ordained: here is no abrogation, but a ratification of this eternall ordinance.</p>
               <p>And laſtly (which in mine opinion is the moſt impregnable place) <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. the Apoſtle ſtrongly prooueth, that the Tithes muſt for euer remaine due vnto God: For being to prooue the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of CHRISTS Prieſt-hood, aboue the Prieſt-hood of <hi>Aaron,</hi> and <hi>Leui,</hi> hee prooueth it by the perpetuitie thereof: becauſe CHRIST remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a Prieſt for euer after the order of <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dec:</hi> whereas the Leuiticall Prieſt-hood was alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ended, &amp; to prooue the perpetuity of Chriſts Prieſt-hood, he vſeth no other <hi>Medium,</hi> but this perpetuall tithing, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8. Here men that did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Tithes, that is <hi>Leui,</hi> who died both in regard of perſon and office: but there, that is CHRIST in <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> receiued them, of whom it is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6518:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>that hee liueth: therefore if Chriſts Prieſt-hood be perpetuall, then muſt his tithing be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall, or els the Apoſtles argument is to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <p>And thus you ſee it prooued by theſe three places of Scripture, that theſe Tithes, which <hi>Iacob</hi> vowed in my Text long before the Law, are ſtill due vnto God, and his Church in the time of the Goſpell <hi>iure Diuino:</hi> And this hath beene both the conſtant opinion of all Antiquitie, and the perpetuall practiſe of the Church, whatſoeuer any late Hiſtorie doth report to the contrary. Therefore it is abſurde to ſay, that theſe Tithes were onely Leuiticall, and that there is now no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a competencie due by a Morall equitie: For how can they be only Leuiticall, which were vowed by <hi>Iacob</hi> in my text,<note place="margin">Heb. 7.8.</note> and paid by <hi>Abraham,</hi> and by <hi>Leui</hi> himſelfe in the loines of <hi>Abraham,</hi> fiue hundred yeeres before the Leuiticall Law began. And to ſpeake of a Competencie now, is a meere conceit: For who ſhall preſume to preſcribe an vncertaine Competencie, where God himſelfe hath ſet downe a perpetuall certaintie, which hee neuer yet altered? Or why ſhould any man think, that God, who prouided a ſtanding, certaine, and liberall Maintenance for the Leuiticall Prieſt-hood in the time of the Law, which was leſſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, ſhould leaue the Miniſtery of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, which exceedeth in honour vnto an vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and beggerly competencie: eſpecially fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing, and foretelling that in theſe laſt dayes
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6518:14"/>Charitie ſhould waxe cold, and men be louers of themſelues, and their pleaſures, more then louers of God, and his Church. And yet hee requireth Hoſpitality at our hands too, which he knew the worlds competency could not affoord.</p>
               <p>Therefore it muſt needs follow for a certaine concluſion, where with I will end, that all true <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobites,</hi> or true <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> which liue vnder the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, are bound to performe all <hi>Iacobs</hi> Vow in the time of the Goſpell, and not onely to haue the Lord for their God, and build, or at leaſt main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his houſes; but alſo, of all that he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them, to giue the Tenth vnto him. And therefore, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>It muſt needs be a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction for any man to deuoure theſe things that are ſanctified,</hi> the vſurping, and deuouring whereof, (as I verily beleeue) hath beene the deſtruction of many Houſes amongſt vs. <hi>Noluimus partiri cum Deo decimas,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Augustine;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Serm. de tem. <hi>219.</hi> cap. <hi>39.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Modo au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem totum tollitur: We would not giue our Tithes vnto God, and now all is taken from vs.</hi> And <hi>Malachi</hi> ſaith, <hi>They are curſed with a Curſe all the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, that robbed the Lord of Tithes and Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings.</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> curſeth the deuourers of theſe holy things, with the moſt bitter curſe, that euer he curſed any creature.<note place="margin">Pſal. 83.</note> O <hi>my God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Doe vnto them that ſay, Let vs take the Houſes of God into our poſſeſsion, as vnto the</hi> Midianites, <hi>as to</hi> Siſera <hi>and</hi> Iabin; <hi>which periſhed at</hi> Endor, <hi>and became as dung for the earth. Make their Nobles like Oreb, and Zeeb: yea all their Princes, as Zeba and Zalmunna:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6518:15"/>make them like a wheele, and as the ſtubble before the wind: As the fire burneth the wood, and as the flame ſetteth the mountaine on fire; ſo perſecute them with thy tempeſt, and make them afraide with thy ſtorme, &amp;c.</hi> God keepe all our Nobles and Princes, and People from this bitter Curſe: for the auoiding whereof, and obtaining the contrarie bleſſing, me thinkes many ſhould not onely, with <hi>Iacob</hi> in my Text, vow to giue their own Tithes; but vow to redeeme theſe captiue-tithes, out of the hands of other men, who haue vſurped the ſame, and to reſtore them vnto the Lord againe, who is their right owner; then which, they cannot almoſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a more acceptable Sacrifice, or Seruice vnto him.</p>
               <p>And yet how theſe houſes of God are taken, and ſtill helde in poſſeſſion, and his Inheritance ſtill embezelled in theſe dayes, the cryes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the poore Leuites euery where doe witneſſe, not onely in thoſe places, where all is gone, and onely a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency (as it was then ſuppoſed) often pounds a yeere left (which is ſcarce a Competency now for a Hog-heard) but alſo in many other places, where the tithes are not quite impropriated, but yet ſo gelded by pretended preſcriptions, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionable, nay vnreaſonable cuſtomes <hi>de modo decimandi, &amp; de non decimando,</hi> and they many times confirmed by prohibitions, that the poore Leuite hath in ſome places, not the tenth, in ſome, not the twentieth part of the tithe. I would to God that the Body of the Honorable Parliament
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6518:15"/>were as willing as the Religious and Royall Head thereof, to take this grieuance into their ſerious conſideration, that this Parliament might haue the honour to enact ſome wholeſome Law for the honour of God, the aduancement of his Church, the peace of their owne conſciences, and the reliefe of the poore Clergie in this behalfe; that ſo we might all (as we are all bound) pay <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> Vow vnto the God of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and receiue from him <hi>Iacobs</hi> bleſſing. Which God graunt for his Sonne IESVS CHRIST his ſake, who is our eternall Prieſt, to whom with the Father, and his Bleſſed Spirit bee all Honour, Praiſe, and Thankeſ-giulng for euer, and euer.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>John Bill.</hi> 1621.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
